{
  "id": "IIKG3020-Incident-Response-2024",
  "title": "Eksamen IIKG3020 (2024) â€” Multiple Choice Questions (25 points)",
  "description": "Multiple Choice Questions from the IIKG3020 exam 2024. Use for practice and self-testing.",
  "questions": [
    {
      "question": "What comes second of these actions in the NIST incident response lifecycle",
      "choices": [
        "Detection and analysis",
        "Preparation",
        "Containment, eradication and recovery",
        "Post-incident activity"
      ],
      "answerIndex": 0
    },
    {
      "question": "What is the first and most important step that CERT/CC recommends when starting the process of implementing a CSIRT?",
      "choices": [
        "Determine the CSIRT strategic plan",
        "Design the CSIRT vision",
        "Gather relevant information",
        "Obtain management support and buy-in"
      ],
      "answerIndex": 3
    },
    {
      "question": "Which of these metrics would be the most relevant to report to upper management after a cyber incident?",
      "choices": [
        "Number of IDS alerts related to the detected incident",
        "Number of person-hours diverted from normal operations to respond to the incident",
        "Number of false positives diverting SOC personell from the incident",
        "Number of SIEM threat hunting searches performed"
      ],
      "answerIndex": 1
    },
    {
      "question": "Which TLP marking should be used for sharing information that should only be spread on a need-to-know basis within an organisation and its clients?",
      "choices": [
        "TLP Amber",
        "TLP Red",
        "TLP Green",
        "TLP Amber + Strict"
      ],
      "answerIndex": 0
    },
    {
      "question": "What is an example of an atomic indicator?",
      "choices": [
        "File hash",
        "IP address",
        "Regular expression",
        "IDS rule"
      ],
      "answerIndex": 1
    },
    {
      "question": "What would a CVSS score of 10.0 indicate?",
      "choices": [
        "This is a vulnerability of minor severity",
        "This is a very critical vulnerability",
        "This is a very common software security weakness",
        "This is a zero-day vulnerability"
      ],
      "answerIndex": 1
    },
    {
      "question": "What comes first of these in the Mandiant cyber attack life cycle?",
      "choices": [
        "Internal reconnaissance",
        "Move laterally",
        "Escalate privileges",
        "Establish foothold"
      ],
      "answerIndex": 3
    },
    {
      "question": "What is the main goal of intrusion reconstruction according to the intrusion kill chain model?",
      "choices": [
        "Reduce the number of steps the adversary must go through",
        "Increase the adversarial courses of actions across the kill chain",
        "Push detection from the latter phases of the kill chain into earlier ones",
        "Move detection down the kill chain"
      ],
      "answerIndex": 2
    },
    {
      "question": "Which of these indicators would cause the adversary the most amount of pain when you implement detection and response?",
      "choices": [
        "TTPs",
        "Hash values",
        "Domain names",
        "IP addresses"
      ],
      "answerIndex": 0
    },
    {
      "question": "Which of these strategies is typically used in threat hunting?",
      "choices": [
        "Deductive reasoning and hypothesis testing",
        "Automated monitoring",
        "IOC-driven analysis",
        "Analysis driven by Al using ML"
      ],
      "answerIndex": 0
    },
    {
      "question": "Which of these assumptions form the basis of the MITRE ATT&CK model?",
      "choices": [
        "Automated measuring of endpoint data gives telemetry that can not be distinguished from the typical background noise",
        "Adversaries tend to exhibit consistent patterns of behaviour while interacting with victim systems",
        "Defense gaps can be discovered by emulating the attacker pre-compromise behaviour",
        "Pre-compromise operations can be modelled by observing the attacker interactions with endpoints"
      ],
      "answerIndex": 1
    },
    {
      "question": "What is the distinction between a MITRE ATT&CK technique and an IOC?",
      "choices": [
        "IOCs are less dependent on specific malware or hacker tools",
        "ATT&CK techniques cannot be used as input to intrusion detection signature",
        "IOCs have less utility for defenders",
        "Many ATT&CK techniques are legitimate system functions, while IOCs are typically associated with adversary actions"
      ],
      "answerIndex": 3
    },
    {
      "question": "What should be the focus of the incident containment phase?",
      "choices": [
        "Detailed forensics analysis",
        "Attacker attribution",
        "Recovering control of the affected systems",
        "Ransom payment strategy"
      ],
      "answerIndex": 2
    },
    {
      "question": "What is STIX/TAXII?",
      "choices": [
        "A malware sharing platform",
        "A tool to perform campaign analysis using the cyber kill chain model",
        "An extensible XML schema developed by Mandiant",
        "An industry standard for sharing IOCs"
      ],
      "answerIndex": 3
    },
    {
      "question": "What is the most basic and foundational incident response capability in the hierarchy of needs?",
      "choices": [
        "Telemetry",
        "Detection",
        "Inventory",
        "Triage"
      ],
      "answerIndex": 2
    },
    {
      "question": "What is usually the purpose of tuning IDS alarms?",
      "choices": [
        "Minimise false negatives",
        "Minimise true negatives",
        "Minimise false positives",
        "Minimise true positives"
      ],
      "answerIndex": 2
    },
    {
      "question": "What type of IDPS is most likely to detect malware containing a zero-day exploit?",
      "choices": [
        "Automated response IDPS",
        "Signature-based IDPS",
        "Network-based IDPS",
        "Anomaly-based IDPS"
      ],
      "answerIndex": 3
    },
    {
      "question": "What is the least complex adversary tripwire type IDPS?",
      "choices": [
        "Honeynet",
        "Honeytoken",
        "Honeypot",
        "Honeytrap"
      ],
      "answerIndex": 1
    },
    {
      "question": "What type of IDPS presents a single pane of glass view for alert triage and management and automates response actions?",
      "choices": [
        "HIDS",
        "SIEM",
        "SOAR",
        "NIDS"
      ],
      "answerIndex": 2
    },
    {
      "question": "Which IOCs can typically be used for cross-pivoting when analysing malicious network infrastructure?",
      "choices": [
        "TTPs, File hashes and Regular expressions",
        "IDS rules, File hashes and DLLs",
        "Domain names, IP addresses and SSL certificates",
        "Tools, Malware artefacts and TTPs"
      ],
      "answerIndex": 2
    },
    {
      "question": "What is the purpose of threat intelligence forecasting?",
      "choices": [
        "Getting ahead of the attack lifecycle",
        "Input to the root cause analysis",
        "Getting ahead of the indicator life cycle",
        "Responding after the point of compromise"
      ],
      "answerIndex": 0
    },
    {
      "question": "Which of these is typically a host-based indicator?",
      "choices": [
        "Malware artefacts",
        "Communication protocol",
        "Domain name",
        "Hosting provider"
      ],
      "answerIndex": 0
    },
    {
      "question": "What is the most important step in the threat intelligence cycle?",
      "choices": [
        "Collection",
        "Analysis and production",
        "Dissemination",
        "Planning and direction"
      ],
      "answerIndex": 3
    },
    {
      "question": "What is an example of CSIRT reactive services?",
      "choices": [
        "Intrusion detection services",
        "Technology watch",
        "Vulnerability handling",
        "Security audit or assessments"
      ],
      "answerIndex": 2
    },
    {
      "question": "Which one of these claims related to legal frameworks for CSIRT information sharing is true?",
      "choices": [
        "IP addresses are not considered personal data according to GDPR",
        "The NIS2 directive gives a stronger legal provision for CSIRT information sharing than GDPR",
        "GDPR is not applicable to CSIRT information sharing",
        "GDPR does not allow CSIRTs to share information containing personal data"
      ],
      "answerIndex": 1
    }
  ]
}